A Guide to the Papers of the Charlottesville Garden Club 1949-2004
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Charlottesville Garden Club 1949-2004
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12508
This collection consists of ca. 800 items (5 Hollinger boxes and 3 cubic boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, by Lois Elliott on April 18 and May 6, 2003, and January 21 and March 18, 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Chartlottesville Garden Club was founded March 17, 1949 and became a member of the Garden Club of Virginia, May 15, 1957. It was incorporated November 16, 1983.
Scope and Content
The Charlottesville Garden Club papers consist of ca. 800 items (5 Hollinger boxes and 3 cubic boxes), 1949-2004. The papers consist of meeting minutes (annual, board, monthly), reports (annual, club committees, financial), photographs and negatives, scrapbooks, and historical materials of the Charlottesville Garden Club. Annual reports are more elaborate for later years and include reports submitted by various Club committees, i.e., the Admissions Committee, the Special Arrangements Committee, the Daffodil Test Chairman, etc. Financial reports are included for some years. Completeness of annual reports varies with only minimal information for earlier years. Annual reports were submitted in the spring of each year (April) covering the previous 12-month period. Scrapbooks include photographs, newspaper clippings, flyers, letters, and other materials concerning club activities and special events. Photographs show Club events (annual shows and meetings, competitions, special events), floral arrangements, and club members.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the following series: I. Annual Reports, II. Meeting Minutes, III. Miscellaneous Papers, IV. Negatives, Photographs, and Scrapbooks. Annual Reports and Meeting Minutes are arranged chronologically. Miscellaneous Papers are arranged alphabetically by subject. Negatives and Photographs are separated into groupings which contain 1) only negatives, 2) only photographs, and 3) both photographs and negatives and are arranged alphabetically by subject within groupings. Scrapbooks are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Contents List
- Annual Reports
  - Annual Reports Charlottesville Garden Club 1967-1990 April (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Annual Reports Charlottesville Garden Club 1990 May-1993 April (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Annual Reports Charlottesville Garden Club 1993 May-1996 April (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Annual Reports Charlottesville Garden Club 1996 May-1998 April (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Annual Reports Charlottesville Garden Club 1998 May-2003 April (Box-folder 1:5)
- Minutes of Meetings
  - Minutes of Meetings (Monthly and Annual) 1966-1970 April (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Executive Board and Monthly) 1968-1975 February (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Executive Board and Monthly) 1975 March-1979 April (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Board, Executive Committee, and Monthly-including Annual Report 1980-1981) 1979 May-1981 October (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Executive Committee and Monthly) 1981 November-1983 October (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Executive Committee and Monthly) 1983 November-1984 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Board, Annual, General Membership, General Business, Monthly) (including Annual Reports) 1984-June 1988 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Board, Monthly) 1988 August-1990 April (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Board and Monthly) and Attendance Records 1990 May-1992 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Board, Monthly, and Annual) and Attendance Records 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Board and Monthly) and Attendance Records 1995-1998 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Executive Committee, Monthly, Annual) 2002-2004 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Miscellaneous Papers
  - The Activities of the Charlottesville Garden Club (Biennial Reports) 1971-1999 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Albemarle, Rivanna, and Charlottesville (A.R.C.) Garden Club/Piedmont Environmental Council A.R.C. Natural History Day Camp; and Nature Camp 1970-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Articles of Incorporation of the Charlottesville Garden Club, and, By-Laws of the Charlottesville Garden Club 1983, 1997 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle Council of Garden Clubs (Constitution-June 1984, Annual Report 1985/1986, Meeting Minutes-September 11, 1989, Programs-1992/1993, Representatives Reports-April 15, 1998) 1984-1998 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - "An Entertaining Experience" with Keith H. Knost (a special event concerning interior design sponsored by the Charlottesville Garden Club) 1992 May 20-21 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Fraternities (Fraternities/Garden Club Project) 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Fraternities (Sigma Nu, Delta Kappa Epsilon, Sigma Phi, Kappa Sigma) 1987 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Fraternity Houses/Carr's Hill 1987-1988, (4 items) (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Fraternity Landscaping Contest 1979-1980 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Garden Club of Virginia Materials (Submitted by Charlottesville Garden Club for History of the First 50 Years of the GCV), and Meeting of Board Members and Committee Heads and Board of Governors Meeting 1993-1994, 1998 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Historic Garden Week 1980, 1988 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Historic Garden Week 1997 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Historical Materials (Histories, Reminiscences, Newspaper Articles) of the Charlottesville Garden Club 1957-2003 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Historical Materials (Histories, Reminiscences, Newspaper Articles) of the Charlottesville Garden Club 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Member Survey, Charlottesville Garden Club 1994 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Members Biographies and Resignations 1994, 2003 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Miscellaneous Materials (Invitation, Thank You Note, Letter about Lockwood Frizzell, Membership Directory, etc.) 1965-2002, n.d. (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1970-2001, n.d. (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Rose Committee Notes of Ann Crigler, Rose Test Chair 1949-2002 (Box-folder 4:15)
- Negatives, Photographs, and Scrapbooks
  - Negatives - Annual Show, Westminster Canterbury and Sheila's Workshop (September 1994); Sherry Hale Arrangement and Annual Show (September 1995); Silent Auction (December 1995); Unidentified (n.d.) 1994-1995, N.D. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Photographs - Annual Meeting and Daffodil Show Leftovers (1995); Daffodil Show (1992); Extra Pictures Addressed To Jane Maddux (1991?); Luncheon at Ashlawn (May 11, 1995); Martha Jefferson Hospital Rooftop Garden; Rose Show, Winchester-Clarke G.C. (October 1995); Rotunda Campaign Gala (October 1995); Unidentified (n.d.) 1991-1998, n.d. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Photographs and Negatives - Board of Governors Meeting, 3 folders (Box-folder 5:3-5)
  - Photographs and Negatives - Charlottesville Garden Club's Visit to Stratford Hall (June 21, 1995); Daffodil Show, Ashland (1995); Duplicates, Odds and Ends (1991, 1994); Flower Show, Colonnades (1992); Flower Show, University Village Flower Show Extra Pictures (September 1991); Flower Shows, Rose Show (1995); Garden Club Daffodil Show, Cocktail Party at Hunter Smith's (1993-1994); Kelly Wedding, Lily Show, Stratford Hall (1995) 1991-1995 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Photographs and Negatives - Sheila MacQueen (1994); Unidentified, Trying New Camera (1994), Wedding F.C.C. (n.d.) 1994, n.d. (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Scrapbooks - Application of Charlottesville Garden Club for Common Wealth Award (Landscaping of Five Fraternities as Community Project) 1988, volumes 1-2 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1953-1960 (Volume 3)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1961-1973 July (Volume 4)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1973 July-1982 (Volume 5)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1983-1991, volume 6 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1992-1994 June, bolume 7 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1994 April-1996 April, volume 8 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1996 April-1997 August, volume 9 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1997 September-1998, volume 10 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks - Charlottesville Garden Club 1999-2000, volume 11 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook - Charlottesville Garden Club 25th Anniversary 1957-1982, volume 12 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook - The Fiftieth Annual Daffodil Show 1984, volume 13 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook - Garden Club of Virginia Board of Governors Meeting 1998 October, volume 14 (Box 8)